<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" version="3.3.0" xml:id="Fein-Owl-098-Art24-Proverbs-Alfred-Headnote-tei">
    <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
 <titleStmt><title>Introduction to The Proverbs of Alfred</title><author>Fein, Susanna</author><sponsor>The University of Rochester</sponsor>
 <sponsor>TEAMS: Teaching Association for Medieval Studies</sponsor>
 <funder>National Endowment for the Humanities</funder>
 <funder>The University of Rochester</funder>
 <funder>TEAMS: Teaching Association for Medieval Studies</funder><respStmt><persName>Conklin, Ashley R.</persName><resp>Audited documents prior to print/export</resp><resp from="2022-05" to="2023-09">Entered corrections for digital edition</resp><resp from="2022-05" to="2023-09">Entered corrections for print edition</resp></respStmt><respStmt><persName>Delcourt, Steffi</persName><resp from="2024-02" to="2024-05">Audited documents prior to print/export</resp><resp from="2020-07" to="2021-12">Checked and corrected bibliographic references</resp><resp from="2020-02" to="2020-03">Copyedited and proofread</resp><resp from="2020-07" to="2023-11">Ensured adherence to METS Style Guide</resp><resp from="2022-05" to="2023-11">Entered corrections for digital edition</resp><resp from="2020-02" to="2023-09">Entered corrections for print edition</resp><resp from="2020-02" to="2020-03">Formatted for print edition</resp><resp from="2020-02" to="2023-11">Formatted for XML export</resp><resp from="2024-05" to="2024-06">Encoded TEI</resp></respStmt><respStmt><persName>Kephart, Daniel</persName><resp from="2024-02" to="2024-05">Audited documents prior to print/export</resp><resp from="2023-10" to="2023-10">Collected metadata</resp><resp from="2023-11" to="2024-01">Ensured adherence to METS Style Guide</resp><resp from="2023-11" to="2024-01">Entered corrections for digital edition</resp><resp from="2023-11" to="2024-01">Formatted for XML export</resp><resp from="2024-07" to="2024-07">Uploaded / Published digital edition</resp></respStmt><respStmt><persName>Lupack, Alan</persName><resp from="2021-11" to="2021-11">Copyedited and proofread</resp><resp from="2021-11" to="2021-11">Ensured adherence to METS Style Guide</resp><resp from="2021-11" to="2021-11">Reviewed edition for consistency and audience</resp><resp from="2021-11" to="2021-11">Reviewed edition for content and scholarship</resp><resp from="2021-11" to="2021-11">Wrote reader report</resp></respStmt><respStmt><persName>Norris, James</persName><resp from="2024-02" to="2024-05">Collected metadata</resp><resp from="2024-07" to="2024-07">Uploaded / Published digital edition</resp></respStmt><respStmt><persName>Peck, Russell A.</persName><resp from="2021-11" to="2021-11">Copyedited and proofread</resp><resp from="2021-11" to="2021-11">Ensured adherence to METS Style Guide</resp><resp from="2021-11" to="2021-11">Reviewed edition for consistency and audience</resp><resp from="2021-11" to="2021-11">Reviewed edition for content and scholarship</resp><resp from="2021-11" to="2021-11">Wrote reader report</resp></respStmt><respStmt><persName>Price, Eleanor</persName><resp from="2024-02" to="2024-05">Audited documents prior to print/export</resp><resp from="2023-10" to="2023-11">Ensured adherence to METS Style Guide</resp><resp from="2023-10" to="2023-11">Entered corrections for digital edition</resp><resp from="2023-10" to="2023-11">Formatted for XML export</resp><resp from="2024-05" to="2024-06">Encoded TEI</resp></respStmt><respStmt><persName>Yee, Pamela M.</persName><resp from="2021-11" to="2024-05">Audited documents prior to print/export</resp><resp from="2021-11" to="2021-12">Checked and corrected bibliographic references</resp><resp>Collated and entered corrections</resp><resp from="2021-11" to="2021-12">Copyedited and proofread</resp><resp from="2021-11" to="2021-12">Ensured adherence to METS Style Guide</resp><resp from="2021-11" to="2021-12">Reviewed edition for consistency and audience</resp><resp from="2021-11" to="2021-12">Wrote reader report</resp></respStmt></titleStmt><editionStmt><edition>Encoded in TEI in 2024</edition>
 </editionStmt>
 <publicationStmt>
 <publisher>The Rossell Hope Robbins Library, University of Rochester</publisher>
 <pubPlace>Rochester, NY</pubPlace>
 <address>
 <addrLine>https://www.library.rochester.edu/spaces/robbins</addrLine>
 </address>
 <publisher>The Department of English, University of Rochester</publisher>
 <pubPlace>Rochester, NY</pubPlace>
 <address>
 <addrLine>https://www.sas.rochester.edu/eng/</addrLine>
 </address>
 <publisher>TEAMS: Teaching Association for Medieval Studies</publisher>
 <address>
 <addrLine>https://teams-medieval.org/about/</addrLine>
 </address>
 <distributor>The Rossell Hope Robbins Library, University of Rochester</distributor>
 <pubPlace>Rochester, NY</pubPlace>
 <address>
 <addrLine>https://www.library.rochester.edu/spaces/robbins</addrLine>
 </address>
 <availability status="restricted">
 <p>Downloading shall be restricted to one copy for private use.</p>
 </availability>
    <date/>
 </publicationStmt><seriesStmt>
 <title level="s">The Middle English Text Series</title><respStmt><persName>Mead Bowen</persName><orgName>University of Rochester</orgName><resp>Mellon Fellow in the Digital Humanities, Editorial Staff</resp></respStmt><respStmt><persName>Theresa Coletti</persName><orgName>University of Maryland</orgName><resp>Member, Advisory Board</resp></respStmt><respStmt><persName>Ashley R. Conklin</persName><orgName>University of Rochester</orgName><resp>Staff Editor, Editorial Staff</resp></respStmt><respStmt><persName>Rita Copeland</persName><orgName>University of Pennsylvania</orgName><resp>Member, Advisory Board</resp></respStmt><respStmt><persName>Lisa Fagin Davis</persName><orgName>Medieval Academy of America</orgName><resp>Member, Advisory Board</resp></respStmt><respStmt><persName>Steffi Delcourt</persName><orgName>University of Rochester</orgName><resp>Staff Editor, Editorial Staff</resp></respStmt><respStmt><persName>Margaret Dull</persName><orgName>University of Rochester</orgName><resp>Director of Metadata Strategies, Technical Support Staff</resp></respStmt><respStmt><persName>Susanna Fein</persName><orgName>Kent State University</orgName><resp>Associate Editor, Editorial Board</resp></respStmt><respStmt><persName>John Geck</persName><orgName>Memorial University of Newfoundland</orgName><resp>TEI Consultant, Technical Support Staff</resp></respStmt><respStmt><persName>Alexandra Gillespie</persName><orgName>University of Toronto</orgName><resp>Member, Advisory Board</resp></respStmt><respStmt><persName>Thomas Goodmann</persName><orgName>University of Miami</orgName><resp>Member, Advisory Board</resp></respStmt><respStmt><persName>Thomas G. Hahn</persName><orgName>University of Rochester</orgName><resp>Consulting Editor, Editorial Board</resp></respStmt><respStmt><persName>David A. Lawton</persName><orgName>Washington University in St. Louis</orgName><resp>Member, Advisory Board</resp></respStmt><respStmt><persName>Michael Livingston</persName><orgName>The Citadel</orgName><resp>Member, Advisory Board</resp></respStmt><respStmt><persName>Alan Lupack</persName><orgName>University of Rochester</orgName><resp>Associate Editor, Editorial Board</resp></respStmt><respStmt><persName>Peter Nowak</persName><orgName>University of Rochester</orgName><resp>IT Support Specialist, Technical Support Staff</resp></respStmt><respStmt><persName>Katie Papas</persName><orgName>University of Rochester</orgName><resp>Section Supervisor, The Robbins Library, Technical Support Staff</resp></respStmt><respStmt><persName>Russell A. Peck</persName><orgName>University of Rochester</orgName><resp>General Editor, Editorial Board</resp></respStmt><respStmt><persName>Eleanor Price</persName><orgName>Eastman School of Music at the University of Rochester</orgName><resp>Staff Editor, Editorial Staff</resp></respStmt><respStmt><persName>David Raybin</persName><orgName>Eastern Illinois University</orgName><resp>Member, Advisory Board</resp></respStmt><respStmt><persName>Eve Salisbury</persName><orgName>Western Michigan University</orgName><resp>Member, Advisory Board</resp></respStmt><respStmt><persName>Anna Siebach-Larsen</persName><orgName>University of Rochester</orgName><resp>Associate Editor, Editorial Board</resp></respStmt><respStmt><persName>Lynn Staley</persName><orgName>Colgate University</orgName><resp>Member, Advisory Board</resp></respStmt><respStmt><persName>Jeff Suszczynski</persName><orgName>Univeristy of Rochester</orgName><resp>Web Applications Programmer, Technical Support Staff</resp></respStmt><respStmt><persName>Victoria Szabo</persName><orgName>Duke University</orgName><resp>Consulting Editor, Editorial Board</resp></respStmt><respStmt><persName>David Wallace</persName><orgName>University of Pennsylvania</orgName><resp>Member, Advisory Board</resp></respStmt><respStmt><persName>Bonnie Wheeler</persName><orgName>Southern Methodist University</orgName><resp>Member, Advisory Board</resp></respStmt><respStmt><persName>Pamela M. Yee</persName><orgName>University of Rochester</orgName><resp>Assistant Editor, Editorial Board</resp></respStmt></seriesStmt>    
 <sourceDesc>
 <biblStruct>
 <monogr><author>Thomas of Hales</author><author>Unknown</author><editor>Fein, Susanna</editor><editor role="translator">Fein, Susanna</editor><title>The Owl and the Nightingale and the English Poems of Oxford, Jesus College, MS 29 (II)</title><imprint>
 <publisher>Medieval Institute Publications</publisher>
 <pubPlace>Kalamazoo, MI</pubPlace><date>2022</date></imprint>
 </monogr>
 </biblStruct>
 </sourceDesc>
 </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
  <projectDesc>
        <p>The Middle English Texts Series offers a diverse and representative array of literary texts that medieval readers in the present-day British Isles would have encountered between the twelfth and sixteenth centuries. It is committed to making available both affordable print and open access editions to scholars, teachers, and students of the Western Middle Ages. In its digital publications, the series prioritizes a user-friendly interface and viewing options, multiple downloadable formats, enhanced searchability and filtering, and accessibility to the widest possible range of users.</p>
      </projectDesc>
      <editorialDecl>
        <p>METS takes as its mission the creation of affordable editions that would pass scrutiny from the most demanding expert, yet would prove comprehensible, and even enticing, to someone who had never read Middle English before. This agenda dictates that METS publications offer not a critical edition reflecting all surviving manuscripts, and certainly not a diplomatic edition, but a best-text edition, informed by the notes and apparatus of earlier editions (where these exist), and by substantive variants from other manuscript witnesses. Transcriptions of Middle English texts are lightly modernized to ensure a smooth reading experience, while non-English texts preserve both the original language and a modern English translation in facing-page format. Each edition offers expert assistance with language and lexicon, providing glosses alongside the text(s), textual and explanatory notes, elucidation of unfamiliar contexts and traditions, and thematic and interpretive possibilities. All editions feature general introductions that set the edited text within its own time, place, and traditions, and link it to ancestor, congener, and successor materials. All publications contain comprehensive, current bibliographies of pertinent scholarship and criticism. House style is adapted from the <hi rend="italic">Chicago Manual of Style</hi>.</p><correction>
          <p>This text may include corrections made after the original edition went to press in order to correct errors and improve glosses. For a full list of editorial and typographical corrections made to this edition, please view its correction log on Github: https://github.com/mets-editions/fein-owl/blob/main/fein-owl-export-corrections-log.docx</p>
        </correction></editorialDecl><schemaRef url="https://metseditions.org/schema/mets-editions.xsd"/>
 </encodingDesc><profileDesc><langUsage><language ident="en">English, Modern (1500-present)</language></langUsage></profileDesc></teiHeader>
    <text><body xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><anchor xml:id="Fein-Owl-098-Art24-Proverbs-Alfred-Headnote"/><div type="text">
 <p style="bodyfirst" n="1">The Jesus 29 version of <hi rend="italic">The Proverbs of Alfred</hi> consists of twenty-three sections written as punctuated prose paragraphs by the scribe. After a two-section introduction, each section declares a nugget of proverbial truth — pious adage, good manners, social mores, or marital advice — ascribed to the ninth-century Anglo-Saxon king, a king to whom Henry III traced his ancestry (see Paris, <hi rend="italic">The History of Saint Edward</hi>, trans. Fenster and Wogan-Browne, p. 12). What follows is a summary of the content by section:</p>
 <list rend="numbered">
 <item style="indent1">Alfred was wise in law and in words, powerful, and loved God’s work.</item>
 <item style="indent1">Alfred spoke wise words to the people.</item>
 <item style="indent1">God is the supreme King.</item>
 <item style="indent1">A king must be intelligent and learned.</item>
 <item style="indent1">Nobles must judge justly; knights must keep order, defend land, keep peace.</item>
 <item style="indent1">Education is benefical; ignorance is not.</item>
 <item style="indent1">Wealth is worthless without wisdom and friends.</item>
 <item style="indent1">One’s situation can change for the better; God gives us our destiny.</item>
 <item style="indent1">Strive in youth to gain wealth for old age and for God.</item>
 <item style="indent1">Many expect long life, but only God knows when a death will occur.</item>
 <item style="indent1">Property is temporary and from God. Avoid pride over it.</item>
 <item style="indent1">Do not trust in wealth and gain God’s anger; it would be better not to have been born.</item>
 <item style="indent1">Wit and wisdom are better than wealth.</item>
 <item style="indent1">Keep sorrow to yourself; do not give an advantage to your enemy.</item>
 <item style="indent1">Marry a good wife; choose character over beauty.</item>
 <item style="indent1">Do not share private thoughts with your wife; she’ll disparage you before your enemies.</item>
 <item style="indent1">Choose and train a wife well. She should work hard; the husband should be her master.</item>
 <item style="indent1">Woman gives cold counsel. Do not listen to your wife, yet a good woman is a good thing.</item>
 <item style="indent1">Beware of false friends.</item>
 <item style="indent1">Shun bad habits. Instead, be beloved, acquire friends; thereby be fortunate and able to travel.</item>
 <item style="indent1">Everything is transitory, so follow Christ’s will, as Solomon counseled.</item>
 <item style="indent1">Do not blab everything before anyone; be discreet.</item>
 <item style="indent1">Teach your child good habits. He’ll be a comfort or a scourge in your old age.</item>
 </list>
 <p style="bodysubection">The third to fifth sections of the Jesus 29 <hi rend="italic">Proverbs</hi> establish the outlook on social order that one finds concisely stated in <hi rend="italic">Ten </hi><hi rend="italic">Abuses</hi> (art. 15), and the final section treats the eighth abuse: “child unthewed.” According to this medieval model, good social order is hierarchical: God is supreme, king is next, and nobles and knights perform essential duties. The cultivation of wisdom and wit (treated as one noun) is also extremely important: education, literacy, and the application of one’s intelligence form the grounds of good governance (section 4) and, likewise, a good life (sections 6–7). Subsequent sections bring the advice to an individual level, offering wise moral guidance designed to bring about a fortunate life.</p>
 <p style="body" n="1">Compared to other English texts in Jesus 29, aside from <hi rend="italic">The Owl and the Nightingale</hi> (art. 2), there is relatively little concern shown for the perils of the afterlife. The advice given in <hi rend="italic">Proverbs</hi> is largely for the here and now. The last section is about one’s progeny being well taught, well behaved, and a comfort in one’s old age: “Wis child is / Fader blisse” (lines 296–97). “Blisse” does not here refer to heaven as it does in almost every other Jesus poem, but to pride in one’s family descendents. This aspect of <hi rend="italic">Proverbs</hi> makes it more like the collection of English adages in <hi rend="italic">Hending</hi>, found in MS Harley 2253, than like the hell-fire moralizing of <hi rend="italic">The Saws of Saint Bede</hi> (art. 4), found in both Jesus 29 and Digby 86. <hi rend="italic">Proverbs</hi> is also a very apt manuscript companion for <hi rend="italic">The Owl </hi><hi rend="italic">and the Nightingale</hi>, where avian disputants copiously quote the “sayings” of “King Alfred,” although most of the proverbs they spout are not to be found in the <hi rend="italic">Proverbs</hi> tradition.</p>
 <p style="body" n="2">Because its vocabulary is almost exclusively of direct Old English derivation, and because ancient letter-forms appear in some manuscripts, the date of <hi rend="italic">Proverbs</hi> has been of great interest. The most recent assessment sets its composition in the twelfth century, but proposals have ranged from pre-Conquest to the mid-thirteenth century (South, ed., <hi rend="italic">The Proverbs of Alfred Studied</hi>, p. 24). Ascription of the sayings to Alfred is by popular tradition not fact. As Hall notes, it “rests on no firmer ground than an affectionate remembrance of the great king as a sage and teacher of his people” (2:294).</p>
 <p style="body" n="3">The unusual meter of <hi rend="italic">Proverbs</hi> strongly evokes an older Anglo-Saxon style: “The system is that of Layamon and the <hi rend="italic">Bestiary</hi>; . . . a mixture of the national alliterative verse loosely constructed and rhyming couplets. The latter are bound together by perfect, imperfect, even inflectional rhymes, and assonances” (Hall, 2:292). Scholars have determined that the Jesus 29 copy of <hi rend="italic">Proverbs</hi> is the youngest and most scribally-tampered copy to survive (Arngart, ed., <hi rend="italic">The Proverbs of Alfred. II.</hi>, p. 135; South, ed., <hi rend="italic">The Proverbs of Alfred Studied</hi>, p. 23). The Jesus scribe sometimes tends to expand by adding new lines. Hall comments that a “poem of such loose structure readily lends itself to selection on the part of the copyist; and the scribe of MS. J was evidently a critic” (2:295; see also 2:293). But given the distance in time of all manuscripts from the original, no copy is flawless. Hall groups the “dilapidations wrought by the copyists” under six categories: 1) rejection of archaic and uncommon words; 2) modernization of older forms and constructions; 3) rearrangement of words, often into a prose order, spoiling rhyme and rhythm; 4) transposition of lines and parts of lines; 5) a free use of padding; and 6) distortion of rhymes by the substitution of alien dialectic forms (2:293–94). Reading <hi rend="italic">Proverbs</hi> from any of its manuscripts requires, therefore, allowances as to meter, vocabulary, and rhythm.</p>
 <p style="body" n="4">Most of the editorial and critical apparatus surrounding <hi rend="italic">The Proverbs of Alfred</hi> dates from the nineteenth to mid-twentieth centuries and is little designed to welcome modern readers to the work. The text survives in two other manuscripts plus a third one now lost because of the fire in 1731 that destroyed a portion of the Cotton collection. Records of the MS Cotton Galba A.xix copy exist only in pre-1731 transcriptions of differing quality and completeness. On the early transcriptions and the manuscripts, see Hall, 2:285–87; Arngart, ed., <hi rend="italic">The Proverbs of Alfred. II.,</hi> pp. 11–37; South, ed., <hi rend="italic">The Proverbs of Alfred Studied</hi>, pp. 3–11; and Arngart’s earlier study, <hi rend="italic">The Proverbs of </hi><hi rend="italic">Alfred. I.</hi> (1942). <hi rend="italic">Proverbs</hi> varies in every copy; sections differ in number and in order. The present edition, based on Jesus 29, does not provide comparative readings among the different manuscripts, only those among the different editions of the Jesus text. Many editions providing texts from the other manuscripts exist, and nearly every edition cited here prints two or more versions. For a good listing of editions, see <hi rend="italic">DIMEV</hi> 714. The Cambridge manuscript, TCC, MS B.14.39, may be viewed digitally at <ref target="https://mss-cat.trin.cam.ac.uk/Manuscript/B.14.39-40" type="external">https://mss-cat.trin.cam.ac.uk/Manuscript/B.14.39-40</ref>.</p>
 <p style="body" n="5">Two matters of presentation in this edition require special notice. The first one regards meter and layout. In copying each section as punctuated prose, the Jesus scribe did not present <hi rend="italic">Proverbs</hi> in a verse layout, only a loosely rhythmic one. While most editors (for example, Morris and Treharne) have set out the Jesus 29 <hi rend="italic">Proverbs</hi> in uniformly short lines determined by scribal punctuation, I follow a method similar to that of Hall and sanctioned by the scribe’s copying of many long lines elsewhere: lines that alliterate are set as long lines with caesuras; lines that rhyme are set as short lines without caesuras. The second matter regards the placement of the tag “Thus queth Alvred.” By editorial convention, the tag heads each section, but, in fact, the Jesus scribe usually sets it at the <hi rend="italic">end</hi> of a section. This manner — intoning “So says Alfred” at section-ends — mirrors the style of <hi rend="italic">Hending</hi>, where every stanza closes in a proverb followed by “Quoth Hendyng” (<hi rend="italic">CHMS</hi>, 3:220–37). The Jesus scribe’s section divisions are therefore preserved here.</p>
 <p style="body" n="6">For recent critical commentary on <hi rend="italic">The </hi><hi rend="italic">Proverbs of Alfred</hi>, see Cannon, “Proverbs and the Wisdom of Literature”; and Yeager, <hi rend="italic">From Lawmen to Plowmen</hi>, pp. 99–120.</p>
 <p style="bodysubection">[Fols. 189r–192r. <hi rend="italic">NIMEV</hi> 433. <hi rend="italic">DIMEV</hi> 714. Louis, <hi rend="italic">MWME</hi>, 9:2974–75, 3358–60 [42]. <hi rend="bold">Quires</hi>: 4–5. <hi rend="bold">Meter</hi>: 318 lines, irregular rhyme, irregular alliteration, in sections of varying length. The style is that of late Old English, with some lines not alliterating, some rhyming. <hi rend="bold">Layout</hi>: Twenty-three sections, each written as punctuated prose, headed with large colored initials. <hi rend="bold">Editions from MS Jesus 29</hi>: Wright-Halliwell, 1:170–88; Morris, pp. 102–38; Skeat; Borgström, pp. 26–41; Hall, 1:18–28, 2:285–308; Arngart, ed., <hi rend="italic">The Proverbs of Alfred. II.,</hi> pp. 71–150; Treharne, pp. 443–55. <hi rend="bold">Three other </hi><hi rend="bold">MSS</hi>: London, BL, MS Cotton Galba A.xix (lost by fire); Cambridge, TCC, MS B.14.39, fols. 85r–87v; Maidstone, Kent, Maidstone Museum, MS A.13, fol. 93r. <hi rend="bold">Extracts from </hi><hi rend="bold">MS Jesus 29</hi>: Morris-<hi rend="italic">Specimens</hi>, pp. 146–52, 332–33; Sisam and Sisam, eds., <hi rend="italic">The Oxford Book of Medieval English Verse</hi>, pp. 10–11 (section 7 only). <hi rend="bold">Translations (based on TCC)</hi>: Kemble, ed. and trans., <hi rend="italic">The </hi><hi rend="italic">Dialogue of Salomon and Saturnus</hi>, pp. 225–48; Segar, trans., <hi rend="italic">A Mediæ</hi><hi rend="italic">val Anthology</hi>, pp. 127–32. <hi rend="bold">Seventeenth-century transcription</hi>: Aberystwyth, National Library of Wales, MS Peniarth 120, pp. 601–17, by Welsh antiquary Edward Lluyd, Assistant Keeper (1683–1689) and Keeper (1691–1709) of the Ashmoleian Museum, Oxford (Hill-History, p. 203n1; and Hill-Part2, p. 276).]</p>
 </div></body></text></TEI>
